Learn ML molecular dynamics by building it — from F=ma to foundation models.
Molecular dynamics is just F=ma in a loop. The only hard part is knowing the force.
Classical writes the force by hand — fine for argon, broken for real chemistry. AI learns it from data.
An MD engine in ~60 lines of NumPy — atoms move…
…and total energy stays flat — the first sign the simulation is honest.
Lennard-Jones can't tune bond strength, and its tail is the wrong physics for a real bond.
Energy becomes a neural network — and the forces come free from autograd.
Rotate the system or reorder the atoms — the energy must not change. That constraint IS the design.
Modern potentials are geometry-aware graph neural networks.
Load MACE-MP (trained on ~160,000 DFT calcs) and simulate water zero-shot: O–H bond 0.97 Å, close to experiment.
A learned potential can fail silently out of distribution — the trajectory looks fine but the physics is wrong. Committee uncertainty catches it.
Periodic boundaries give a surface-free bulk liquid — no evaporation, fixed density.
The RDF settles to 1 at large r — the signature of a real bulk liquid — and we read off a diffusion coefficient (reduced units).
The physics is tested, not asserted: forces match the gradient of the energy, and energy stays conserved.
Eight runnable notebooks · a tested NumPy engine · MIT · github.com/spacegiyou/atoms-from-scratch